<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Oscar techblog</title><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://oscarlsson.se/</id><updated>2016-10-25T10:18:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Insights driven design at Spotify presented at Nordichi '16</title><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/insights-driven-design-nordicchi.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-25T10:18:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-10-25T10:18:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Oscar Carlsson</name></author><id>tag:oscarlsson.se,2016-10-25:/insights-driven-design-nordicchi.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Me and our Product Designer BjörnLindberg gave a talk at Nordici '16 at
Lindholmen, Gothenburg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NordiCHI is a biennial conference functioning as the main Nordic forum
for Human-Computer Interaction (HCI) research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this talk is inspired by Dan McKinleys presentation and my previous Data in development but has got a 
design perspective that was well received among the HCI researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/GEaq96azZp3WE6"
width="595" height="485" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0"
scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px;
margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div
style="margin-bottom:5px"&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a
href="//www.slideshare.net/OscarCarlsson1/insights-driven-design-at-spotify"
title="Insights driven design at Spotify" target="_blank"&gt;Insights driven
design at Spotify&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target="_blank"
href="//www.slideshare.net/OscarCarlsson1"&gt;Oscar Carlsson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gp.se/nyheter/sverige/gp-se-hyllades-bland-j%C3%A4ttar-som-spotify-och-volvo-1.3901625"&gt;http://www.gp.se/nyheter/sverige/gp-se-hyllades-bland-j%C3%A4ttar-som-spotify-och-volvo-1.3901625&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="PublicSpeaking"></category><category term="ProductDevelopment"></category></entry><entry><title>Mine Out West at Hack Out West 2016</title><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/mine-out-west.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-11T10:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-11T10:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Oscar Carlsson</name></author><id>tag:oscarlsson.se,2016-08-11:/mine-out-west.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As part of a hackathon called Hack Out West we built the Way Out West 2016
festival into minecraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We generated the landscape from maps, built the stage areas and
implemented so that the artists/bands spawned at the right stage when they
were going on stage. All great fun. Watch the video below to check it out
:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="../images/mineoutwest.jpg" alt="Mine out west" style="width: 500px;" &gt;
&lt;img src="../images/hackoutwest.png" alt="Hack out west" style="width: 100px;" &gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MVv6T7Z6TZc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/hackoutwest2016/MineOutWest"&gt;All the code can be found on GitHub here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="hacking"></category></entry><entry><title>Data in development @ Spotify presentation Sigma</title><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/data-in-development-sigma.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-02T10:18:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-05-02T10:18:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Oscar Carlsson</name></author><id>tag:oscarlsson.se,2016-05-02:/data-in-development-sigma.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I gave a presentation at &lt;a href="http://sigmaitc.se/"&gt;Sigma it consulting&lt;/a&gt; on
Lindholmen, Gothenburg, about Data in development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience consisted of consulting developers and managers working on companies
such as Ericsson. I wanted to share our story of early validations and
measuring user impact to validate features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk is inspired by Dan McKinleys presentation but reflects what I
work with and what I spend my time thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/qwkJEQoIqRkMEU"
width="595" height="485" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0"
scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px;
margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div
style="margin-bottom:5px"&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a
href="//www.slideshare.net/OscarCarlsson1/data-in-development-spotify"
title="Data in development @ Spotify" target="_blank"&gt;Data in development
@ Spotify&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target="_blank"
href="//www.slideshare.net/OscarCarlsson1"&gt;Oscar Carlsson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="PublicSpeaking"></category><category term="ProductDevelopment"></category></entry><entry><title>Machine Learning class at Chalmers</title><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/chalmers-machine-learning-class.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-06T10:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-03-06T10:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Oscar Carlsson</name></author><id>tag:oscarlsson.se,2015-03-06:/chalmers-machine-learning-class.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I gave a 45 min presentation at the Machine Learning class at Chalmers
titled "Big Data and Machine Learning @ Spotify". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just recently taking the course as a student I tried to connect the theoretical parts presented in
the course with what the industry does and needs. As data processing and
cleaning of data is a big part in industry but rightfully skipped in a ML
class I mentioned that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/OscarCarlsson1/big-data-and-machine-learning-spotify"&gt;Please have a look at the presentation on slideshare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/Koa6MYPwY0tEu0"
width="595" height="485" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0"
scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px;
margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div
style="margin-bottom:5px"&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a
href="//www.slideshare.net/OscarCarlsson1/big-data-and-machine-learning-spotify"
title="Big data and machine learning @ Spotify" target="_blank"&gt;Big data
and machine learning @ Spotify&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a
target="_blank" href="//www.slideshare.net/OscarCarlsson1"&gt;Oscar
Carlsson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="PublicSpeaking"></category><category term="MachineLearning"></category><category term="Clustering"></category></entry><entry><title>Introduction to Clustering @ Machine Learning meetup</title><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/clustering-meetup-talk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-07T10:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-02-07T10:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Oscar Carlsson</name></author><id>tag:oscarlsson.se,2015-02-07:/clustering-meetup-talk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I gave a talk on introduction to clustering and feature engineering at the Machine Learning meetup-group in Gothenburg. This post includes the links to presentations and abstract.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I gave a &lt;em&gt;introduction to clustering&lt;/em&gt; at the Machine Learning meetup-group here in Gothenburg with 35 Machine Learning-enthusiasts, in a wide range of ML-experience, participating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, Spotify, hosted the meetup at our Gothenburg office and I gave two presentations on roughly 30 minutes each. The first one was a theoretical introduction to clustering and feature engineering.
The purpose of the presentation was to first build an intuition of what clustering is (and what it isn't) by pedagogically explaining the steps from getting the data to the output of the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, as I'm really excited about the Machine Learning-community in Python I demoed some data mining in Python. Showing of the use-everyday-libraries such as Numpy, Pandas and Scikit-learn and tie it together with the theoretical methods I had already explained. The clustering examples I did were on Music Lyric data scraped from a lyrics Wikipedia. I showed how we easily could pre-process (clean / vectorize) the data and then plug it into our clustering algorithms. As problem of clustering is unsupervised hence hard to evaluate I (think) managed to show a typical work flow when doing Machine Learning on real-world data. There were tons of obvious preprocessing steps I skipped, but I did so to not add to much to the presentation but to make it easy to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I must say that I enjoyed talking to all of you attending the event both in the break and afterwards. I noticed that most participated to meet and discuss Machine Learning with others and I'm glad we got the chance to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Material I references to in the talk:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Latest on our Rec Sys : 
&lt;a href="http://www.a1k0n.net/spotify/ml-madison/"&gt;http://www.a1k0n.net/spotify/ml-madison/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep Learning at Spotify: 
&lt;a href="http://benanne.github.io/2014/08/05/spotify-cnns.html"&gt;http://benanne.github.io/2014/08/05/spotify-cnns.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My presentation:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/theoretical.slides.html"&gt;Presentation 1: Theoretical introduction to Clustering and feature engineering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/python_demo.slides.html"&gt;Presentation/demo 2: Introduction to data (mining) analysis in Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the last part, after mentioning iPython, was demoed live in the notebook. Get the notebook at
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Oscarlsson/meetup-clustering-presentation"&gt;Github repot&lt;/a&gt;
and try it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="PublicSpeaking"></category><category term="MachineLearning"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="Scikit-learn"></category><category term="Clustering"></category><category term="FeatureEngineering"></category></entry><entry><title>Who is doing Machine Learning in Gothenburg?</title><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/machinelearninggothenburg.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-01-22T16:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-01-22T16:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Oscar Carlsson</name></author><id>tag:oscarlsson.se,2015-01-22:/machinelearninggothenburg.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The machine learning community in Gothenburg is small but existing. This is a summary of how to get in touch with it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a master student majoring in Machine Learning I've tried to research what
companies and institutions in Gothenburg that is involved in Machine Learning/Big data/Data analysis. I was
looking for future work place and trying to understand how the community in GBG worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I would share what I've found.
This list is probably not complete and I would love to add information about your company or 
research group as well as update or change the information given below.
The Machine Learning community in Gothenburg is not big which partly motivates this summary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The community&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, &lt;a href="http://karinabunyik.com"&gt;Karina Bunyik&lt;/a&gt;, started a meetup group for Machine Learning Gothenburg &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Goteborg-Machine-Learning-Meetup/"&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt; that I'm now co-organizing.
There will be seminars introducing the basics of Machine Learning and hopefully presentations from the industry on applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, that it is besides what Chalmers offers. The ML group at the Computer Science department is called LAB and announces seminars on this &lt;a href="http://www.cse.chalmers.se/research/lab/seminars.php"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;. I find
it useful to skim once a month or so.
Not to long ago LAB helped arrange a &lt;a href="http://www.cse.chalmers.se/research/lab/seminars.php?sid=25"&gt;Seminar on Big Data&lt;/a&gt; at Chalmers indicating that the community is growing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Chalmers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chalmers offers a couple of interesting courses. Nothing in data mining but some in statistics and theoretical ML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cse.chalmers.se/research/lab/courses.php?coid=9"&gt;Algortihms for Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://physics.gu.se/~frtbm/joomla/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=99&amp;amp;catid=79&amp;amp;Itemid=290A"&gt;Neural Networks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.math.chalmers.se/Stat/Grundutb/GU/MSA100/A13/"&gt;Computer Intensive Statistical Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cse.chalmers.se/edu/year/2013/course/TIN171/"&gt;Artificial Intelligence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cse.chalmers.se/research/lab/courses.php?coid=8"&gt;OLD: Decision Making Under uncertainty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cse.chalmers.se/research/lab/courses.php?coid=4"&gt;OLD: Boosting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Industry&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Recorded Future&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recorded Future is a startup company headquartered in Cambridge, MA with offices in Arlington, VA and Gothenburg, Sweden. Their team includes computer scientists, statisticians, linguists, and technical business people with deep expertise in areas such as intelligence and security. They`re committed to organizing the web in a radically new and useful way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have heard, and seen job ads, indicating them looking for Data Scientists and Machine Learning engineers. Their dataset contains billions of texts and the tool they are developing is a way to analyze it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know they have had collaborations with Chalmers LAB group in exchanging data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jobs here: &lt;a href="https://www.recordedfuture.com/jobs/"&gt;RF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Findwise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Findwise uses search technology to increase your data quality. Our motto is "right information, to the right person, at the right time".  We have had over 300 successful project in different industries and areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, as Recorded Future they have had collaborations with Chalmers LAB group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On their website they announce that they are looking for thesis students in Machine Learning &lt;a href="http://career.findwise.com/jobs/2110-thesis"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I recall one thesis-description including experimenting with word2vec.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Burt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burt provides intelligence and analytics to digital publishers, 
turning big data into insight, action and revenue. Our platform is built to support digital media owners, rather than online marketing 
and e-commerce. We combine detailed media measurement, powerful big data capabilities and beautiful data visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the two previous companies Burt is a pure startup in company culture. It is hard to understand how they are using Machine Learning but they seem to be running A/B-tests and use some type of large NoSQL-database for their 700TB data. That indicates to me that they are one of few interesting companies to mention in a summary as this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An old thesis of a evaluation of storage of large data can be found &lt;a href="http://publications.lib.chalmers.se/records/fulltext/123839.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and 2014 this thesis was announced &lt;a href="https://farmchalmers.files.wordpress.com/2014/02/thesis_work_original_a4.pdf"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tajitsu&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tajitsu is a predictive customer analytics platform for progressive marketing teams. We help companies find high-value customers, and keep them coming back. Tajitsu turns data into results!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tajitsu is focusing on helping Casino-companies understand their data. Meaning that they build Machine Learning-models they selll business-to-business.
No job advertisements out but they are looking for Machine Learning engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Aitellu&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aitellu delivers Insight Analytics of Big data to give you information detecting anomalies and nascent trends, helping you to act on the things that make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heavily connected with Tajitsu as the people behind Tajitsu left Aitellu to start their own business. One of the algortihms used at  Aitellu is a so called evolutionary algortihm.
As for jobs: they where looking for &lt;a href="http://www.wannaremote.com/utvecklare-at-aitellu-technologies-ab-gothenburg-sweden-allows-remote/"&gt;python-developer with knowledge in AI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dreamler&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dreamler's mission is to enable people to experience true efficiency and constant improvement, across all projects. Our product harnesses the competitiveness, speed, and seamless teamwork of multiplayer games to realize your biggest ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure what data Dreamler has but this blog post indicates that they are at least interested in Machine Learning &lt;a href="http://blog.dreamler.com/machine-learning-in-dreamler/"&gt;http://blog.dreamler.com/machine-learning-in-dreamler/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Spotify&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music streaming service&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spotify do have an office in Gothenburg, but no team focusing on Machine Learning. The recommender system-team is located in NYC and former EchoNest in Boston. However, I'm working as a Data Engineer (in Gothenburg) doing data analysis on our large dataset from a performance perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="MachineLearning"></category><category term="Gothenburg"></category><category term="Chalmers"></category><category term="DataMining"></category></entry><entry><title>ia32libs on 64-bit Debian Wheezy</title><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/ia32libs.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-07-02T10:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-07-02T10:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Oscar Carlsson</name></author><id>tag:oscarlsson.se,2014-07-02:/ia32libs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short guide on how to get 32-bit programs working on a 64-bit debian wheezy using ia32libs.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tried to install a VPN earlier, Forticlient SSL VPN, on my 64-bit Debian wheezy but it turned out to only exist a 32 bit version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# My system:&lt;/span&gt;
$ uname -a
$ Linux lad-laptop 3.2.0-4-amd64 &lt;span class="c1"&gt;#1 SMP Debian 3.2.57-3+deb7u2 x86_64 GNU/Linux&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After googling for solutions the standard reply was to install a library which would make 32-bit programs just work: &lt;code&gt;ia32-libs-gtk&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So i tried this, with no luck:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following packages have unmet dependencies: &lt;br&gt; ia32-libs : Depends: ia32-libs-i386 but it is not installable &lt;br&gt; E: Unable to correct problems, you have held broken packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I found a couple of guides but everyone differed in something. I will now retell what worked for me.
First I had to tell the package management, dpkg, that I wanted &lt;code&gt;i386&lt;/code&gt; libraries (32bit)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ dpkg --add-architecture i386
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;then change the lines in &lt;code&gt;/etc/apt/source.list&lt;/code&gt; to look like following&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;deb&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sx"&gt;[arch=amd64,i386]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kp"&gt;http://ftp.se.debian.org/debian/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kp"&gt;wheezy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kp"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And then update the system with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ sudo apt-get update &lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; sudo apt-get dist-upgrade 
$ sudo apt-get install &lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; sudo apt-get dist-upgrade
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;and then I was able to install the ia32-lib and get Forticlient working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ sudo apt-get install ia32-libs-gtk &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; sudo apt-get install libgtk2.0-0:i386
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note: I have still not gotten any errors by allowing i386 libs on my system but I will update this post if anything bad happens.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Debian"></category><category term="Notetoself"></category><category term="Unix"></category></entry><entry><title>IPython Notebook on Amazon</title><link href="http://oscarlsson.se/notebookonremote.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-19T18:13:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-06-19T18:13:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Oscar Carlsson</name></author><id>tag:oscarlsson.se,2014-06-19:/notebookonremote.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Working on IPython Notebook is convenient but not always feasible when working on large datasets. This shows how I used a EC2-instance to allow me to work on larger sets.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I mainly work in Python which has the wonderful tools IPython Notebook
and IPython QT console, both supporting interactive python and inline
matplotlib plots. Notebook has the benefit of cell execution and I use it
when iteratively analysing a dataset and QT console when developing the 
infrastructure to later on use in the analysis. This post will talk about the
analysis in IPython Notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often when doing quick and dirty data analysis we're able to work locally on our laptops
but sometimes that dataset is to large or the computation to heavy. Moving away from
the normal tools and libraries that we're used to and work on distributed frameworks can be
cumbersome. Luckily we can host a Notebook on a Amazon EC2 instance and leave the computation
over night or use a offering with more RAM or CPU than we have locally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When working on my master thesis I used one of the bigger offerings from Amazon with 70GB RAM and
8 cores, allowing me to run multiple tests in parallel by different notebooks.
&lt;/br&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src="../images/amazonperformance.png" alt="Amazon" style="width: 500px;" &gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;
These steps are really simple. On the Amazon instance, start a IPython Notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ipython&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;notebook&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;7777&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On the local machine, set up a ssh-tunnel to the EC2 instance on that port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ssh&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;N&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;L&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;localhost&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;7777&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;localhost&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;7777&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;amazon&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;where amazon is defined in the ssh-config.
Navigate to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:7777&lt;/code&gt; and you will access the notebook running on the EC2 instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;tips&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To easy pass variables between notebooks use the predefined ipython commande, %store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Save a variable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;store&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;variable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Retrieve a variable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;store&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;variable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;and to see what variables are currently set, use&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;whos&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of things not working properly in Notebook. One of which is that when
closing the connection from the browser, the output of a running execution gets lost. This is 
already reported as a bug and apparently hard to fix with the current codebase.
The solutions is to store intermediate results in a file but this of course means messier code.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="iPythonNotebook"></category><category term="Amazon"></category><category term="Thesis"></category></entry></feed>